Inventory of the Helen Praeger Young Interviews
Hoover Institution Archives
Helen Praeger Young interviews
1985-2002
1985-1997
2008C52
Young, Helen Praeger, 1932-, interviewer.
10 manuscript boxes, 4 cassette boxes (5.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives
Sound recordings and translations of transcripts of interviews of women veterans of the Chinese Long March of 1934-1935. Used as research material for the book by Helen Praeger Young, Choosing Revolution: Chinese Women Soldiers on the Long March (Urbana, 2001).
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection mainly contains sound recordings and translations of transcripts of interviews of women veterans of the Chinese Long March of 1934-1935 used as research material for the book by Helen Praeger Young, Choosing Revolution: Chinese Women Soldiers on the Long March (Urbana, 2001). Additionally, the collection contains research material in both English and Chinese, such as biographical material about the women interviewed, the Long March, maps of China, caligraphy samples, and other printed material and drafts of various editions of the book with comments from editors and peers at the "Stanford Biographers Seminar."
China--History--Long March, 1934-1935.; Communism--China.; Phonotapes.; Women--China.
- Sound recordings of interviews, 1986-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  On compact sound cassettes. Titles taken directly from labels.
  - Chen Zongying sound recordings from June 1987, 20-27 June 1987; Four compact sound cassettes (Box 11)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008574
    Parts 1-4: 20 June 1987 Parts 4-8: 27 June 1987
  - Deng Liujin, 1st Interview, 2 compact sound cassettes (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008434
    Transcript in English available in Box 1
  - Deng Liujin, 2nd Interview, 1 July 1986; Three compact sound cassettes. The third cassette also contains part of the third interview with Deng Liujin (Box 11)
    The third cassette contains part of the third interview. Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008439
  - Deng Liujin, third interview, Two compact sound cassettes. Part of the third interview is contained on the last cassette of the second interview (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008438
    Part of the third interview is contained on the last cassette of the second interview
  - 12-11-86 interview, 11 December 1986; Two compact sound cassettes (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008422
  - Guo Chen interview, 10 July 1986; One compact sound cassette (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008573
  - He Manqiu interview, 15 March 1987; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview. The first is two cassettes long. The second is three cassettes long. (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008572
  - Jian Xian Jo interview, 3 September 1988; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, both 3 cassettes long each. (Box 11)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008456
  - Jian Xianren interview, 5 December 1988; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, 3 cassettes each. (Box 11)
    Transcript in English available in Box 1.
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008578
  - Jian Xianren interview, 10-17 December 1988; Two compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, two cassettes each.
    Parts 1-3: 10 December 1988 Part 4: 17 December 1988
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008579
  - Jian Xianren interview, 14 December 1988; Two compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, two cassettes each. (Box 11, Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008582
  - Interviews with old soldiers and others, 15 and 17 June 1997; One compact sound cassette (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008586
  - Kang Keqing interview, 14 January 1987; Two compact sound cassettes (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008441
  - Li Gui Ying and Wei Xiu Ying interviews, 9-11 February 1989; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, one 3 cassettes long and the other 1 cassette long. (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008587
  - Li Jianzhen and Xie Xiaomei interviews, 2 February 1988; Two compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, two cassettes each. (Box 12)
    Use copy reference numbers: 2008c52_a_0008428
  - Li Kaifen interview, part 1, 28/10, Beijing, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008461
  - Li Kaifen interview, part 2, 28/10, Beijing, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008462
  - Li Yun Ja interview, 14 June 1988; Two compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview. One is one cassette long and the other is two cassettes long. (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008696
  - Lin Yueqin interview, 26 Jan 1988; Three compact sound cassettes (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008698
  - Liu Jian interview, 29 January 1988; One compact sound cassette. There are two copies of this interview, each one cassette long. (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008715
  - Liu Jian interview, 30 January 1988; Four compact sound cassettes (Box 12)
    Use copy reference numbers: 2008c52_a_0008440, 2008c52_a_0008723, and 2008c52_a_0008724
  - Liu Jian interview, 29-30 January 1988; One compact sound cassette (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008728
  - Liu Ying interview, 27 January 1988; One compact sound cassette. There are two copies of this interview, each one cassette long. (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008432
  - Music recordings and Liu Ying sound recording, 27 January 1988; One compact sound cassette (Box 12)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008727
    Part 1 is two music pieces.
    1. A Taste of Honey 2. Le Petite Melodie
    Part 2 is a woman speaking in Chinese.
  - Ma Yixiang interview, 1 February 1988; 5 compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of the interview, one five cassettes long and the other four cassettes long. (Box 13, Box 12)
    Use copy reference numbers: 2008c52_a_0008397 and 2008c52_a_0008452
    The copy 2008c52_a_0008397 copy includes an interview with Li Jianzhen from 2 February 1988
    Transcript in English available in Box 2.
  - Ma Yi Xiang 2 Chao Youp Hua sound recording, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008455. Transcript in English available in Box 2.
  - Quan Wei Hua interview, 10 July 1987; Three compact sound cassettes (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008791
  - Qian Xijun interview, 23 August 1988; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, each three cassettes long. (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008801
  - Qian Xijun interview, 27 August 1988; Three compact sound cassettes (Box 13)
    Use copy number: 2008c52_a_0008816
  - Wang Ding Guo interview, 6-7 June 1986; Three compact sound cassettes (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008830
  - Wang Quanyuan and Wei Xiu Ying interviews, 12-13 February 1989; 7 compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of these interviews, each seven cassettes long. (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008840
    Wang Quanyuan, Tai Hu; Wei Xiu Ying interviews, Nanchang
    The interview changes from Wang Quanyuan to Wei Xiu ying at the beginning of part 11 in the Panasonic version and in part 11 in the Sony version.
    The first tape of both copies is missing, although this beginning of the interviews might be at the end of item 2008c52_a_0008955.
  - Wei Xiu Ying interview, 11 February 1989; Two compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, each two cassettes long. (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008955
    This recording series may also include the first parts of the Wang Quanyan interview from 12 February 1989.
  - Xiao Ku, Lin Yue Qin, etc, interview, undated; Two compact sound cassettes (Box 13)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008956
  - Xie Fei interview, 22 October 1988; 6 compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, each six cassettes long. (Box 14)
    Use copy number: 2008c52_a_0008957
  - Xie Xiao Mei interview, 2 February 1988; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview, each three cassettes long. (Box 14)
    It appears that the beginning of this interview is on the cassettes with an interview with Li Jianzhen (use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008428).
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008959
  - Yan Jing Tang interview, undated; Two compact sound cassettes (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008967
  - Zhang Gue Lin interview, 16 February 1989; Three compact sound cassettes. There are two copies of this interview. The first copy is two cassettes long. The second and third copies are three cassettes each and the third appears to be a direct copy of the second. (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008972
  - Xiao Lin's father-in-law interview, 8 June 1997; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008982
  - Zhang Wen interview, 17 Jul 1987; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008983
  - Zhang Wen interview, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy number: 2008c52_a_0008985
  - Hunan sound recordings, 14-15 June 1997; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Label reads: [illegible], Lu Jiaping 6/14/1997, 97 year old, side A, interview with 97 year old woman who cared for He Jie Chang after LM; Tao Wo 6/14/1997, 74 year old, side B; 6/15, Jiang Jia Jie - 2, Red Army Vets, hu and gang,
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008989
  - Sound recordings from 23-25 June 1997, One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Label reads: 6.23.97/Keen [ming?], 4th Front Army 1/4, Wang Chao 6.25.97/Li Jiang, Li Jian Bowoguan, director - Li Xi
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008992
  - Unidentified sound recording from 15 June 1997, One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0008996
  - Educational sound recordings read by Helen Praeger Young, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Part 1 is "Shrewd Todie and Lyzer the Miser" by Isaac Singer
    Part 2 is "The Kingdom of Kochen"
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0009000
  - Unidentified interview sound recording, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy number: 2008c52_a_0009003
  - Unidentified sound recording, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0009007
  - Unidentified sound recording, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    The sound quality is terrible on the accessioned cassette.
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0009006
  - Unidentified sound recording, undated; One compact sound cassette (Box 14)
    Use copy reference number: 2008c52_a_0009010
- Interview files and transcripts, 1985-1995
  Contains transcripts of interviews, biographical notes on subjects, and drafts of chapters incorporating interviews with maps and scanned photos included.
  - Chen Zongying, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Biographical/Historical note
    Chen Zongying joins the Long March in August 1934 in the Sixth Army Group.
  - Deng Liujin, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Deng Liujin was a First Front Army veteran.
  - He Manqiu, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    He Manqiu was a Fourth Front Army veteran.
  - Jian Xianfo (Mei Mei), 1988-1995 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Jian Xianren (Jui Jui), 1989-1995 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Jian Xianren was a Second Front Army veteran.
  - Kang Keqing, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Kang Keqing was the wife of the commander-in-chief of the army, Marshal Zhu De. Keqing was transferred from the First Front Army to the Fourth Front Army in June 1935.
  - Li Guiying, 1989 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Li Jianzhen, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Li Yanfa, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Liao Siguang, 1988 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Lin Yueqin, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Lin Yueqin was a Fourth Front Army veteran, joined the Long March in 1932.
  - Liu Jian, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 1: 12-13)
  - Liu Ying, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Ma Yixiang, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 2-4)
    Ma Yixiang was a Second Front Army veteran; she joined the army at age 11.
  - Qian Xijun, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Quan Weihua, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    Quan Weihua was a Fourth Front Army veteran.
  - Wang Ding Guo, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2: 7-8)
    Wang Dingguo was a Fourth Front Army veteran.
  - Wang Quanyuan, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Wang Quanyuan was transferred from the First Front Army to the Fourth Front Army in June 1935. In 1936, Quanyuan commanded a regiment of women.
  - Wei Xiuying, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Xie Fei, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2: 11-12)
  - Xie Xiaomei, 1988 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Zhang Wen, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    Zhang Wen was a Fourth Front Army veteran.
  - Zhang Yuan Yuan, 1985 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Yan Jingtang, 1985 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Men's interviews and mixed materials regarding Chinese Communist Forces, 1944-1985 (Box-folder 2: 17)
- Research material and drafts
  - Maps and printed material on China and the Long March, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Notes and drafts, "He Manqiu's Story,", 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Drafts, "Jian Xianren,", 1994 (Box-folder 3: 3-5)
  - Drafts, "Women's Voices on the Long March" and "Women Soldiers of the Long March,", 1992-1994 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Drafts, notes, and printed material, 1995 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Drafts with notes from "Biographers Seminar,", 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3: 8-10)
  - Research material, and drafts with notes from "Biographers Seminar,", 1994 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Drafts with notes, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Drafts and working outlines, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "The Feminist Press" drafts and materials, 1996 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Drafts, correspondence, and printed material, 1985-1993 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - United Nations Association research materials, undated (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Maps of China, undated (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Preliminary list of maps by chapter, 2000 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Wang Yougin's calligraphy for book, undated (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Maps of China, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Book photographs by chapter, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Printed material, eye witness accounts, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Maps of China, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Articles on women and oral history, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Biographical sketches, lists, 1986-2002 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Huaxia Funu Mingren Cidian, 1988 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Long March Images, scanned pictures and photographs, undated (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
  - Chinese source material on the Long March, Chinese women, undated (Box-folder 5: 9-10)
  - Various interview notes, circa 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Drafts with Susan Rigdon/Cropp's comments, undated (Box-folder 5: 12-13)
  - Drafts with notes, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Stanford "Biographers Seminar" presentation and comments, 1994 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
  - Introduction draft before revisions, 1999 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Thesis: "Women and the Chinese Communist Party,", 1978 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - "The Private Life of Chairman Mao,", undated (Box-folder 6: 6-8)
  - Articles and publications, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 6: 8-9)
  - Articles, 1990s (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Wang Yizhi: A Woman in Revolution," Gilmartin and Stranahan, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
  - Papers and articles on women's issues, women in politics, 1986-1997 (Box-folder 7: 4-7)
  - Research trip photographs, itinerary, maps, 1997 (Box-folder 7: 8-9)
  - "Choosing Revolution," proof and notes, 2001 (Box-folder 7: 10-12)
  - Manuscript preparation guidelines, 1999 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Drafts with Susan Rigdon comments, 1999 (Box-folder 8: 2-3)
  - Architectural sketches and articles, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Drafts, notes, research materials, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 8: 5-6)
  - Early correspondence and proposal, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Copies of face sketches, undated (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Chinese Map, undated (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - University of Illinois Urbana Press "Choosing Revolution" proposal and draft, 1997 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Biographical notes, chapter notes, 1997 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Articles on Chinese communist politics, 1994 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Publications and drafts, on women and war, 1995 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
  - "Women's Voices on the Long March" notes and chapter drafts, 1994 (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
  - "Will to Survive," "Choosing Revolution" drafts and proposals, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - "Women on the Long March," "Women's Voices" chapter drafts, 1993 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - "Women on the Long March" chapters, 1993 (Box-folder 9: 8-9)
  - "Long March" drafts for writing workshop, 1993 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - Printed material on Chinese communist party, politics (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Zheng Peijun's research, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Long March, first front notes (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Writings, drafts regarding the organization of the Long March, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Dijkstra/Dykstra Literary Agency material and correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - "The Rise of the Chinese Communist Party,", 1972 (Box-folder 10: 8)